<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A supplycacion to our moste soueraigne lorde Kynge henry the eyght Kynge of England of Fraunce and of Irelande, [and] moste ernest defender of Christes gospell, supreme heade vnder God here in erthe, next [and] immedyatly of his churches of Englande and Irelande.</title>
            <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1544</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24165.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898124</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898124</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2086:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A supplycacion to our moste soueraigne lorde Kynge henry the eyght Kynge of England of Fraunce and of Irelande, [and] moste ernest defender of Christes gospell, supreme heade vnder God here in erthe, next [and] immedyatly of his churches of Englande and Irelande.</title>
                  <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1544]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard Tracy.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC; publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Complains of the luxury and inefficiency of the Bishops and clergy.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶.</note>
                  <note>C3r catchword: "ted".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſupplycacion to our moſte ſoueraigne lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Kynge Henry the eyght / Kynge of En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland of Fraunce and of Irelande / &amp; moſte erneſt defender of Chriſtes goſpell / ſupre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me heade vnder God here in erthe / next &amp; immedyatly of his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Englande and Irelande.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matthei .ix.</bibl>
               <p>The harweſte is greate but the laborers are fewe. Wherfore praye the lorde of the harweſte to ſende forthe laborers into his harweſte.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:4"/>
            <head>A ſupplication to our moſte ſoueraigne Lorde Kynge Henry the eyght Kynge of England / of Fraunce / and of Irelande. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt dreade Soueraigne lorde &amp; moſt chriſten Prynce / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I remembre the lamentable, &amp; wonderfull great blyndnes wherin the moſt parte of all Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de not onely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te called the temporaltie / but alſo of the Clergie / haue pytuouſely erred and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered many hundereth yeres / acceptinge / reputynge / &amp; moſt vngodly / erronyouſely / and blyndely / eſtemynge the Byſſhop of Rome to be ſupreame head ouer &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue all chriſten congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: and in dyuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe other poyntes ſuche as be touchynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſarye articles of our faithe. I coulde not but meruell how and by what meanes ſuche peſtilent errours and horrible darke blyndenes coulde or myght entre / Invade &amp; ouerflowe this your realme / &amp; to conty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>newe ſo longe in the ſame / not eſpied / per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued / nor repelled. Conſideringe that by all that tyme and ſpace this your Realme (as the moſt parte of men dyd then iudge
<pb facs="tcp:135564:5"/> and eſteame) was well endowed / repleny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed / and furnyſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many profounde ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned clerkes / wherof ſome were Byſſhops Archedeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / Deanes / Prebendaries / Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons / Doctours / Bachelars in deuinite / &amp; other profounde lerned clerkes in bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſytees which were / graue / ſage / &amp; auncyent fathers. Contemplatinge and reuoluinge theſe things in my mynde: not a lytle moued / troubled / and vexed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / I applyed me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all my powre &amp; dyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence exquyſytely to ſerche &amp; to knowe the originall grounde &amp; cauſe therof. And in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluſyon amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt other things it chaunced me to reade in the .v. chapiter of Ezay a propoſition that muche lamenteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> capty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uite and bondage which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth &amp; grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to all people for lacke of knowleage in godds worde / Sayeng / Therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth my flocke alſo into captyuite / becauſe they haue not vnderſtandinge / their glory is famyſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hunger / &amp; their pryde mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chyrſte. Therfore gapeth hell and openeth her mouthe meruelouſely wyde. By this text graciouſe lorde it appeareth that all myſerable blyndenes captyuite &amp; bondage vnder ſynne / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth for lacke of knowleage in Gods worde.<note place="margin">Mar. xij,</note> I had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at that tyme / that Chriſt reproued the
<pb facs="tcp:135564:5"/> Pharaſees / ſayeng / You erre not knowin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the ſcriptures. Which reproue and rebu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſhulde haue ben a ſuffycient admonycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and doctryne to me and to all other wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we myght haue knowen that all errou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re commeth for lacke of vnderſtandinge &amp; knowleage in the ſcriptures. But by what reaſon then coulde there be ſuche erroure and blyndenes for lacke of knowleage in Gods worde in this your realme moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyouſe lorde / ſeing there were ſuche profoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de clerkes &amp; auncyent fathers / Byſſhops and ſtudentes in the ſame / which dyd tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che &amp; preache vnto the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually. The Apoſtle Paul in the .vi. chapiter to Ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mothe deſcrybeth two kyndes of doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / the one he calleth a godly doctryne &amp; a doctryne of helth / the other he calleth a proude doctrine full of vnprofitable queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / ſtryuynge more for wordes than for godly knowleage / wherof ſpryngeth envy / ſtryffe / raylings / euyll ſurmyſyngs / &amp; vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne dyſputacions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with corrupte myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des deſtytute of the trueth / which thinke that lucre is godlynes. This kynde of ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge and ſubtle dyſputacyons vnto this daye we call ſcole matters / from the which Paul commaundeth all chriſtyans to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues.<note place="margin">ij. Ti. iij</note> Soche clerkes ſayeth Paul / 
<pb facs="tcp:135564:6"/> be euer lernynge / but neuer atteyne to the knowleage of the trueth. With ſuche way<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vngodly and vnprofitable lerninge / this your realme moſt redoubted ſoueraigne was ouer moche replenyſhed through the preachinge and teachinge of ſuche ſcole men &amp; ſubtyll diſputers / otherwiſe called deceyuers. Which was one of the cauſes of our myſerable blyndnes / and of dyuerſe er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours and abuſes ſpronge vp and crept in to this your graces realme. For certeynely if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clerkes of this your graces realme / had bene endowed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true knowleage of Gods worde / and had alſo ſyncerely preached the ſame / althoughe ſuche errours and blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes had entered into this realme / yet they ſhulde neuer haue ſo longe contynewed in the ſame / but we ſhulde haue bene delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red through the worde clerely from them. As Chriſte ſaieth.<note place="margin">Io. viij.</note> If you continewe in my wordes / then are you my very diſciples / &amp; ſhall knowe the trueth / &amp; the trueth ſhall delyuer yow / and make you free. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt dread ſoueraigne lorde / ſeinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all erroure / ſpyrytuall blyndnes / myſerable captyuite / and ſeruyle bondage vnto ſynne commeth for lacke of knowleage and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge in the holy ſcriptures / and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye parte / through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leage
<pb facs="tcp:135564:6"/> &amp; ſyncere vnderſtandinge of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripturs we knowe god our father and his ſonne Iheſus Chriſt our lorde / which is eternall liffe / we be alſo become free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all condempnation of ſynne.<note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. v.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Io. xvij.</note> And through the ſyncere and true knowleage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde we be newly regenerate &amp; become y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne of god / the habitacle and dwellinge place of the holy ghoſte / which moueth &amp; ſteareth vs euer to mortefye the fleſhe / &amp; all her ſynfull luſts and concupiſcence / to abhor and reſyſt vice. What is then ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary good and profitable for the chriſtian people bothe ſpirituall and cyuile wealthe / as the worde wherby we receyue faithe / &amp; by faithe the holy ghoſte. What troubleth all commen wealthes / but treaſon / murder thefte / couetuouſnes / adulterye / extorcion / whordome / dronckenes / periurye / &amp; ſuche other ſynne / as ſaythe the holy ghoſte.<note place="margin">Prouer. xiiij.</note> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and rightuouſnes maketh the people wealthy / but ſynne maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people moſt myſerable. And all theſe the faithfull through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true and ſyncere vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge of gods worde / doo euer ſtudye and labour to ouercome / and vtterly to abholyſhe by faythe. As Paul ſayeth.<note place="margin">Gal. v.</note> They which be Chriſtes / doo crucyfye the fleſhe with her luſtes and concupiſcence. All good workes
<pb facs="tcp:135564:7"/> and counceyles encreaſed and ſtablyſhed through faythe. There is no ſtudy / ſtriffe / nor laboure agaynſt ſynne but through faithe. All conſcyences that be quyet from ſynnes / onely through faythe be made quy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>et.<note place="margin">Rom. v</note> As Paul ſayeth / Becauſe we are iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by faithe / we are at peace with god through our lorde Iheſus Chriſt. What counforte hathe any Chriſtian man in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſytyes / temptacions / deſperation / but onely by fayth in Gods worde. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyan man hathe noo refuge nor helpe to reſyſt ſynne / but onely by gods worde / as our ſauiour chriſt dyd / wherin he muſt fyxe a ſure and conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faythe.<note place="margin">Mat. .iiii.</note> Faythe cauſeth vs and all ours / to be acceptable in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of God.<note place="margin">Roma. xiiij.</note> For a concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whatſoeuer is not of fayth that ſame is ſynne. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>owte a conſtante and ſure fayth / it is impoſſyble to pleaſe God.<note place="margin">Heb. xi.</note> All men maye well perceyue / that by the lawes and by the iuſte execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them / although ſynne may be for a tyme cohybyted and reſtrayned / yet it can not be ſuppreſſed and abholyſhed / but onely through fayth. For there was neuer more godly lawes made for the punyſhmente of ſynne / nor neuer more iuſte and godly ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecutyon of lawes admyniſtred / and yet the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re was neuer more ſynne raygnynge. For
<pb facs="tcp:135564:7"/> cyuyle lawes made by man / can not be of greater effycacye or ſtrength / nor worke greater perfectyon vertue and good wyll in man / than the lawe of god: but the lawe of God not onely worketh no obedyence or vertue / but rather through occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the infirmyte of the fleſhe / ſteareth vp ſynne / as ſayethe Paul.<note place="margin">Ro. vij.</note> I knowe not what luſte dyd meane / except the lawe had ſayed thow ſhalte not luſte. But ſynne toke an occaſyon by the meanes of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente / and wrought in me all maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupiſcence / for verely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute the lawe / ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne was dead. I ones ſayth Paul / lyued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out lawe. But when the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / ſynne reuyued / and I was dead / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame commaundement which was or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deyned vnto lyffe / was founde to be vnto me an occaſyon of deathe.<note place="margin">Ro. vij.</note> But nowe gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſe lorde / for aſmoche as it appeareth / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lawe of God was not geuen to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye ſynne / but rather to declare and to punyſhe ſynne: moche leſſe any lawe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by man / can auoyde and put away ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. But faythe is the true Inſtrument ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by God / wherby ſynne is ouerco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; exiled.<note place="margin">Act. xv</note> As the ſcripture ſayeth / that God through faithe / dothe puryfye &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke cleane all hartes.<note place="margin">Io. xv.</note> Alſo Chriſt ſayethe / 
<pb facs="tcp:135564:8"/> nowe are yow cleane / by the meanes of the wordes / whiche I haue ſpoken vnto you. This faythe ſhall cauſe / noryſhe and breade / true obeydyence / and all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in your graces ſubiectes hartes / wherby they ſhall be enforced to laboure not onely to obſerue &amp; kepe Godes lawes / but alſo all your graces ordynances com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes and lawes / without grud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge or murmuracyon. This faythe as the Apoſtle ſayeth commethe by hearinge of Gods worde preached / wherof Byſhops Parſons / Vicars / &amp; ſuche other called to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſpirituall cure / be or ſhulde be dylygent myniſters / to whoſe vocatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtely partey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth to declare and publyſhe Gods worde ſyncerely &amp; truely / to all the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their ſpirituall charge.<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> Moſt mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prynce wherfor if the Paſtours appoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to preache &amp; teache Gods worde / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this your graces realme / doo not dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly inſtructe &amp; teache the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to their ſpirituall charge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd worde / accordinge as they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.<note place="margin">Act. xx. i. Pe. v. Mal. ij. Proue. xxix.</note> Act. xx. i. Pet. v. and Malache. xx. all kynde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne ſhall increaſe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde / &amp; the people vtterly be devyded. As ſayethe the holy ghoſte. When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God is not preached y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people peryſheth.
<pb facs="tcp:135564:8"/> Alſo the Wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayethe.<note place="margin">Sa. xiij</note> All men be vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in whom there is not the knowleage of god. Wherfore without any doubt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te and lacke of preaching of godes worde ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and truely hathe bene the very origi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall grounde and cauſe of all the inſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / dyſcention / which hathe ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen or begone within this your graces real me or any parte therof. For through the want of preachyng of Godes worde ſynce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly haue entered in all popyſhe blyndenes / vayne &amp; dead ceremonyes / me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be crept into the conſcyences of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple innocentes in the ſteade of the lawe of God. Yea ydolatrye and all hypocryſye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deteſtable ſuperſtycyon for lacke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of Godes worde / is become Gods ſeruyce. And yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandinge this wante &amp; lack of knowleage in Godes worde &amp; the euyll which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>methe manyfeſtly therof / (the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it is to be lamented / ) there be many po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe monckes which late were Abbottes (to whom not onely vnworthely / but alſo vniuſtely / were geven greate penſyons) and many of their covent mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>kes hauin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge nother lernynge nor other godly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytyes (apte meate or convenyent to be in ſpirituall paſtours) be nowe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted to haue cure of ſoules. And
<pb facs="tcp:135564:9"/> ſome ſuche which ded neuer knowe what is a ſoule / nor yet be able to haue cure ouer one ſoule / be nowe admytted to haue char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ouer an hundreth and many moo / to the increaſe of all yngnora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye and all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe blyndnes / the hyghe waye &amp; meanes to let in all kynde of ſynne / to the vtter dampnacion of all the ſoules commytted to their ſpirituall charge. Alas doo nother y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patrones of ſuche benefyces / nor yet the incumbentes po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or regarde Gods thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atenyngs by his Prophete Ezechiell ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeng / As truely as I lyue ſayeth the lorde for aſmuche as my ſhepe are robbed and deuowred of the wilde beaſtes of the felde hauynge noo ſhepeherde / and ſeing that my ſhepherdes take noo regarde of my ſhepe / but feade them ſelues onely / and not my ſhepe.<note place="margin">Ezech. xxxiiij.</note> Therfore here the worde of the lorde o ye ſhepherdes / thus ſayeth the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de God. Beholde I my ſelfe will vpon the ſhepherdes / and requyre my ſhepe from their handes / and make them ceaſe from feadinge of my ſhepe. Yea the ſhepherdes ſhall feade them ſelues nomore / for I will delyuer my ſhepe owte of their mowthes / ſo that they ſhall not deuoure them after this. If this threatenynge be not ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warnynge &amp; monycion to ſuche blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:135564:9"/> ſhepherdes / yet at the leſt let them fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Goddes curſe pronownced in the ſame chapiter agaynſt ſuche neglygent and ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhepherdes / ſayenge. Woo be to the ſhepherdes of Iſraell that feade them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / ſhulde not the ſhepherdes feade the flocke / yow haue eaten vp the fatt / yow haue clothed yow with the wolle / the beſt fedd haue youe flayne / but the flocke haue yow not noryſhed / heauen and erthe ſhall muche rather periſhe / than theſe wordes wherwith God threatened ſuche paſtours ſhalbe found vntrue / That is / I will requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re my flocke of the handes of the ſhepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Suerly moſt myghty prynce it is to buſye an office / tomuche and laborouſe for one ſpirituall ſhepherde (althoughe he were very expert and connynge) to guyde ordre / and kepe / two or thre flockes of ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe / ſpecially beyng ſo farre dyſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t one from an other / that the ſayd ſhepherde can not be dayly preſent with them / to ſe the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernaunce of them / whoſe nature is dayly to falle into dyuerſe offences and ſpirituall dyſeaſes. For the office of a good ſhepherd is not onely to feade his ſhepe in good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture / but alſo to ſeke the loſt ſhepe / to call agayne the ſtrayed ſhepe in to the ryght waye / to ſalue and to make hole y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broken
<pb facs="tcp:135564:10"/> which is broken by aduerſyte / the weake and ſycke ſhepe in the faythe / with the counfortable promyſes of God / declared in the goſpell / to make ſtronge &amp; conſtant: and in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſyon to aduenture his liffe (if nede requyre) for the defence of his ſhepe / ever circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpecte lyeng in wayte / to reſyſt the ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe lyon / whiche neuer ſlepeth / goin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge abowte and ſeakynge whome he maye devoure.<note place="margin">i. Pe. v.</note> Suche I ſaye ſhulde be their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and dayly cure ouer their flocke ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed / that not onely their ſhepe / but alſo all other / ſeing and preceyvinge their grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te paynes and labours ſuſtayned and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the helpe and counforte of their ſhepe / the gentle entertayninge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all pacyence / humylyte &amp; meakenes / the fatherly love / cure / and affeccion which the ſaid byſhops and other Paſtours ſhulde daylye ſhewe / exercyſe &amp; practyſe towardes Chriſtes floc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to their ſpirituall charge ſhall iudge them not onely good ſhepherdes which enter in by the dore / but alſo ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue &amp; take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be moſt ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle / prouyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t kynde / &amp; lovinge ſpirituall fathers. But moſt prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gouernoure how ſhall this fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therly cure / love / zeale / &amp; affection / be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed by the paſtoure to his ſpirituall ſhepe which daylye cowcheth and wayteth in
<pb facs="tcp:135564:10"/> your graces houſeholde and courte / and in other noble &amp; worſhipfull me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes howſes / at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendinge to pleaſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych is called one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſerue God. And not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandinge his callinge to be a ſhepherde to feade Chriſtes flocke / yet he will ſeaſe ſe and viſyte them ones in the yere. And when he viſyteth his ſhepe / what ghoſtely councell he geveth them / God knoweth. But for the more parte / he loketh more to his owne profett than to their wealthe. Alas the ambicyou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe appetyte &amp; burnynge covetuouſe deſyre of the yerely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyties / profettes and ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vauntages of the benefyces / hathe vtterly extynguyſhed and ſupped vp the ſpirituall love / zeale and affection which ought to be in the ſpirituall ſhepherdes. So that nowe it is ſtraunge and wonderfull to ſe or knowe one iuſtely to execute his offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. Is this the honowre of any Kynge or of any other gouernowre / that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cloke and coloure of hys ſeruyce / a Byſhope or Pryſte called to ſeade the flocke of Chriſte / ſhall leaue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vntaught / and ſo tranſgreſſe the commaundement of Chriſte for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of men? Haue not Kynges and other rulers ſufficyent to endowe their cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelaynes / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out retayninge ſuche which
<pb facs="tcp:135564:11"/> haue receyued lyuinge and ſtypende to be in their churches feadinge Chriſtes flock. This is tomoche diſhonoure to the higher powers / agaynſte goddes commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; word to retayne an other mans ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But certenly althoughe your highnes or other rulers wolde nother call nor retayne ſuche ambyciouſe blynde guydes and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſe paſtours / yet they their ſelfe will by their fryndes make importunate ſute and laboure to be in ſeruice with youre mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye and with other rulers. The cauſe is thys / (one inconuenyence graunted / many folowe.<note place="margin">Anno. xxi. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rici. viij</note> There is alawe made in this your noble realme / that all ſpirituall parſons of youre counſell maye haue thre benefyces with cure. And all the chaplaynes of the Kynge / quene / prynce / prynces or of any of the Kyngs children / brethren / ſiſters / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and auntes / maye haue lycence to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue two benefyces with cure. Euery Duke / marques / erle / vycounte / archebyſſhope / byſſhope / with dyuers other eſtates aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well men as women maye haue two chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laynes which maye haue two benefyces w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cure / And alſo dyuerſe other degres of ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le maye haue euery one two benefyces w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cure / ſo that ouer one of his cures althou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe he take the profyttes yet from that
<pb facs="tcp:135564:11"/> he muſte neades be no reſydent and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to bothe he wilbe no feader nor teacher. And alſo in the ſame eſtatute all at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendaunce in the courte and all other atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunces vpon ſuche noble and worſhipfull men which be lycenced to haue chaplaynes maye be not reſydent / yea pylgrymes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of goynge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge from their pylgrymage be by that eſtatute dyſpenced to be non reſydent. O lorde where was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of thy worde / which ſhulde haue bene written in the hartes of the makers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtatute. If there had ben godly ſhepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which had dyligently executyd their office and callynge / we had neuer wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo blyndely to agree or conſent to the makynge of any ſuche eſtatute. Doo we which thinke vs Chriſten men eſteame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall benefyces to be nothinge els but ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinges to be geuen at owre pleaſure to pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes for ſeruyce done? Is not the benefyce geuen in reſpecte of a ſpirituall offyce to be executyd &amp; done? Doth not God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſtraytely ſhepherdes to feade their floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke dyligently? Can man or any lawe made by man dyſpence with Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? O lorde in thy handes be the hartes of all Kynges and other rulers / enlyghten theyr hartes lorde with the light of thy
<pb facs="tcp:135564:12"/> worde that they maye knowe and ſee this peſtylent yll blyndenes / which ſo longe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the cauſed thy ſhepe to wander in darcke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And when they perceyue it they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye haue grace and tyme to reforme the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to thy glory and the helpe of this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. And I ſhall euer deſyer of God and wiſhe in my harte to all ſuche as be called to be attendaunte nere youre mageſtie and all other gouernowres / that for any car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall loue / fauoure / or affectyon whiche they beare to any man for kyndred / frendſhipe / luker / or otherwiſe / they doo not make any ſuche vngodly ſuytes petycions or reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes to your highnes or to any other gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nowre for any parſon to be admytted to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny offyce other ſpirituall or temporall / who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me they doo not certeynly knowe by moſt certeyne and ſure proues and witneſſes / to be apte / meate / and conuenyent aſwell in lernynge as in condycions / to excerciſe vſe and to occupye ſuche offyce and rome / wherunto he by ſuche their ſute made / ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be called / appoynted and admytted (not onely for the ſhame rebuke and troble whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che vpon dewe examynacion had and foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de contrary to their vntrewe ſute) myght come and growe to them / but alſo for the euyll incommodyte and peſtilent myſchef
<pb facs="tcp:135564:12"/> which ſhall enſewe to all ſuche which ſhalbe commytted to his or their gouernaunce &amp; charge. Alas that euer amongeſt the chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten flocke ſhulde be knowen or ſene that ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che office which in Chriſtes churche ſhulde be the moſt godly / moſt neceſſary / moſt ſpirituall and moſt profytable bothe to the bodye and ſowle / nowe is become a worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely honowre / a lordely dygnyte / a riche carnall prowde lyuinge eſtate and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance / and the poſſeſſor therof hauinge one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the name of a ſpirituall minyſter / but no vertue nor godly qualyte which of right ought to be in euery ſuche miniſter. If this be well pondered and remembred moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfull gouernowre / it is moſt to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But ſeynge this blyndnes hathe ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewed &amp; ſomoch ewill hathe enſew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed &amp; folowed therof in the defaulte of godly poſtours / it is not onely nedefull aboue all thinges to be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect in choſynge erneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly cryed / expecte / and well lerned mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to preache Gods worde ſyncerely / but alſo to compell the ſame to be demuran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te abydinge and reſydent vpon their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. And all ſuche whiche be crepte into benefices for luker &amp; aduauntage vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trewe ſuggeſtion and falſe fayned ſutes made / which can not or doo not feade their
<pb facs="tcp:135564:13"/> flocke / to depryue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuche benefyces be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they other can not or doo not execute the offyce to that belonginge. Suerly no wyſe man lyghteth a ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dell and putteth hym vnder a buſhell. And if he ſet vp a ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dell (which other for lacke of talowe or for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe can not geue light) ſhortely he taketh hym downe and putethe an other which can geue good light in his place. So all godly wyſe men will order all ſpirituall lightes which in dede can not geue godly lighte for lacke of ſpirituall grace which ſhulde be in them. For Byſhops and other Paſtors which be choſyne &amp; inſtytuted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the ordynaunce appoynted &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Gods worde / which other doo not or can not execute the offyce perteynin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge to his or their callynge / be not godly &amp; trewe Byſhops but rather Images &amp; Idol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les hauinge and bearinge onely the name and outwarde apparance of a Byſhoppe or Paſtor. But as concernynge the lernyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vertue &amp; other godly qualyties whiche parteyne &amp; be of greate neceſſyte and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce requyſyte to be in euery godly paſtor / they haue nothinge leſſe. For if Chriſt (which ſayed to Peter from henceforthe I make the a fyſher to catche men) doo not endowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offycer wyth lernynge / grace / 
<pb facs="tcp:135564:13"/> power &amp; good will to preache his worde before Patrons preſent hym to any ſuche ſpirituall office / the electe and admytted notwithſtandinge the admyſſion and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons preſentment / <note place="margin">Ioan. x</note> ſhall contynually abyde and remayne an hypocryte / and ſuche one which dothe not enter in by the dore / <note place="margin">Math. xxij.</note> but preſumeth to enter withowte a weddyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge garment / whom Chriſt condempneth to owtwarde darckenes / and alſo callethe hym a thef / whoſe rewarde withowte doubt / ſhalbe at the daye of the laſte iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment with thefes / if he repent not and rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſygne vp hys offyce which he can not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute fulfyll and performe. Wherfore I myſtruſte not but that all ſuche which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue power to preſent and to admytte theyr clerkes to ſpirituall offyces readynge this wele boke for the dyſcharge of theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence and for the glory of God / the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modyte and vtylite of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe (which will enſewe the godly preſentacyon and admyſſion of well lerned / approued &amp; godly clerckes to ſpirituall offyces) will from thenceforthe applye and conforme them to the forme and maner of electyon of ſpirituall myniſters appoynted preſcry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed and lymytted by Godes worde / which is this. That euery man choſyn to vſe any
<pb facs="tcp:135564:14"/> ſpyrituall offyce / ſhulde be fyrſte well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aſwell for theyr lernynge as alſo for theyr other vertuouſe condycions. Fyrſt for theyr lernynge wherwith they muſte not onely be able to enſtructe and teache the people commytted to theyr ſpyrytuall charge / but alſo able to reproue other which reſyſt the ſame doctrine / with many other godly qualyties. As it apperethe in the fyrſte Epiſtle of Paul to Tymothe and alſo to Tyte.<note place="margin">Tim. iij Tyt. i.</note> Nowe moſte myghty defender of the Chriſtyan religyon / ſeinge that Godds worde hathe preſcrybed and declared that euery man which ſhalbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and appoynted to be a ſpyrituall my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter muſte fyrſte be proued and knowen howe godly and ſpirytually he hathe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe and teached the people / what ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge he hathe in the ſcriptures / and not in the lawes / to reproue errours and to condempne hereſyes. What paynes he hathe taken in preachynge Godes worde / and alſo whether he hathe geuen good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of lyuinge accordinge to his doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. In this maner euery chriſtian ought to proue his clerke before he other preſent or admytt hym. But nowe alſo moſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyngne lorde / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydre of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary parte &amp; remembre for what cauſes the Kynges
<pb facs="tcp:135564:14"/> your noble progenitors in tymes paſte ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue choſen Byſſhopps / &amp; other patrons ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue preſented theyr clerckes to perſonagyes &amp; Vicaragyes to haue cure of ſowles. Theſe bothe cauſes well conſydered no man wyll greately meruell that we haue wandered ſo longe in blyndenes. For in tymes paſte Kynges haue geuen theyr Byſſhoprycks to theyr Councellers / chaplaynes whiche haue bene daylye attendauntes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / which alſo haue done to them good ſeruice / as enbaſadoures / or to ſuche which haue taken paynes in theyr houſeholde / as amners &amp; deanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chappell / clercks of theyr cloſett &amp; ſuche other officers / where gods worde dothe not approue any byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ricke to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any ſuche ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice done / or for any ſuche paynes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but onely for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gifte whiche he hathe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God to preache his worde / &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures ſuſteyned in preachinge of the ſayd worde And as Kynges in tymes paſte haue abuſed their giftes of byſhoprikes / ſo noble men &amp; worſhipfull me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergie as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> layere haue abuſed their preſentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to their prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des perſonages &amp; vicarages / geuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their chaplaynes / or to other for kyndred in bloude or for alyaunce / or els to ſuche as haue ben ſurueyours of thier
<pb facs="tcp:135564:15"/> landes / receyuoures of their rentes / ſtuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of their houſholde / faconers / gardyners or to ſuche other whom they fauoure for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che worldely ſeruice &amp; qualyties. To ſuche they geue their benefyces as rewardes or wagies to hyrelynges for ſuche ſeruice do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / or to be done / hauinge lytle or noo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to the great charge and ſpirituall cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re which by Goddes worde belongeth to all ſuche ſpirituall offices. For Kynges and rulers in tymes paſte had noo leſſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage of any thynge / then of Godes worde which the ſubtyll byſhops &amp; crafty pryſtes were euer ſtudiouſe and deſyrouſe to kepe ſecrete from the hygher powers. For ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge as Godes worde was kepte ſecrete and hyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from gouernours / ſo longe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergye dyd leade not onely the Kynges / but alſo all gouernowres &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons whyther they wolde. Thys was the crafty polycye of the clergye / to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowleage of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de from all men / that they myght vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and vnworthely be promoted to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall cures / and vſe the profettes of them vngodly / and that they myght alſo conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually exercyſe their luſtes and iniquyties. As Paul ſaythe They be agaynſte all men forbyddinge vs to ſpeake to the people wherby they myght be ſaued / <note place="margin">The .ij.</note> that they
<pb facs="tcp:135564:15"/> myght fulfyll their iniquyte and ſynne con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynually. Haue not ſome of the byſhops w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their retynewe at this daye practyſed their olde polycy to extinguyſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light through all Englande / that they myght ones agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne leade vs quyetly in darckenes. Is not there a lawe made through their crafte &amp; ſubtylte which geueth power to certayne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſioners wherof the byſhoppes cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unceler or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſarye ſhalbe named to be two of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſioners / which ſhall haue full power to take into their cuſtodye all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bokes wherin is conteyned any clauſe or artycle repugnaunte to any of the ſyx ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tycles / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bokes to burne and dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroye as to the diſcretion of thre of them ſhalbe thoughte expedyent. Marke well what they purpoſe by this eſtatute. Are there any bokes which write agaynſte the popes prymacie / but they alſo write agayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte ſome of the ſyx artycles? Their coloure is to take awaye all bookes which wryte agaynſte the ſyx artycles / but their very in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te purpoſe and meanyng is to take awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye all bookes whiche conteyne any godly lernynge that write agaynſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop of Romes prymacy. Howe cruelly doo the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops punyſhe all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which pretende to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue lernynge and ſpecially in Godds worde?
<pb facs="tcp:135564:16"/> Suche they call heretyques and perſecute wich puttynge them to open ſhame / with enpryſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / and in concluſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the moſt fearefull and paynefull. All this they doo to dyſcorage all men from the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Gods worde / fearinge leaſte that by ſuche ſtudiouſe braynes which learne Gods worde and publyſhe the ſame their iniquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſhulde be made manyfeſt. What ſtudye and paynes they take to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light from the people. But no man which knowethe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures will meruell of this their policye and crueltye.<note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. iij.</note> For ſaynt Iohan declarethe their practyſe playnely ſayenge. He that do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th euyll hateth the light / and why? becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe his workes whiche be euill ſhulde not be reproued by the light. And for aſmuche as oure byſhops countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of lyuinge / their greate poſſeſſyons / and lordely domynyons in them agreeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Godds worde / as dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the with lyffe / God with the deuill / light with darckenes / therfore they hate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light which declarethe the ſame / and ſtudye to ſuppreſſe the ſame by all chaft and polycye. And ſeinge they can ſo craftely iuggle and haue ſuche frendſhipe and fououre to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey / brynge to paſſe / that all bookes ſhall come into their hande &amp; vndre the coloure of the ſyx artycles / it is to be feared that
<pb facs="tcp:135564:16"/> ſhortely they will by lyke crafte ſubtyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and frendſhipe procure the Byble in Englyſhe to be taken from the layete / &amp; then we ſhalbe ledd in darcknenes by our Byſhops and other blynde gydes and not Paſtoures at theyr pleaſure and will / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the effecte of all theyr ſtudy laboure and purpoſe. Nowe moſt valeaunt defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Chriſt / it appearethe playnely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we many myſeryes we be wrapte in / through the vngodly electyon of ſuche as be admytted to haue ſpirytuall cure and offyce to teache Godds worde / whiche not onely haue lytle lernynge / but alſo they be enemyes to all men whiche can and doo preache Gods worde ſycerely and trewly / becauſe they lyue contrarye to the ſame / as I haue before declared / And this is the origynall grownde / and cauſe of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundaunce and increaſe of darkenes and of ſynne / as alſo of the longe contynnaunce of popiſhe blyndnes whiche hathe raigned in this realme ſo longe. Wherfore yf the byſhops and other elected and appoynted to be ſhepherdes accordinge to theyr voca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon and callinge / be not fyrſte knowen and well proued to haue ſuche knowleage &amp; godly doctryne / ſo that they can &amp; alſo doo inſtantely &amp; dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly preache Gods worde,
<pb facs="tcp:135564:17"/> whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light expellinge all darckenes of ſynne / then muſte nedes ſynne encreaſe &amp; abounde without any reſtraynte or brydle. For if the light whiche is amongeſt yow be darckenes / howe muche ſhall the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be?<note place="margin">Matt. vi.</note> Youre grace and your cyuile power doo punnyſhe ſynne / when it is done and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted / accordinge to the iuſtyce of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / as to your vocatyon &amp; office of right belongethe to doo. But the office and dew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye of the Paſtor is to preache Goddes worde / wherby he ſhall conuert the hart of the ſynner / whiche is willinge &amp; diſſpoſed to doo ſynne / ſo that he ſhall not breake fourthe to doo ſynne in the acte / which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyuyle powre for the example of other by equyte and iuſtyce is bounde to punyſhe. Therfore the dyligent executyon of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the paſtoure ſhalbe the pryncipall meane and occaſyon that leſſe ſynne ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted / and ſo the higher powers ſhall haue leſſe occaſyon to execute the extreame iuſtyce of lawes / and conſequently many mens ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es whiche nowe for lacke of the knowleage of Godes worde ſhuld be loſte for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttinge murder / felonye / and ſuche other offences / ſhall then be preſerued that they ſhall not commytte ſuche offences / which the hygher powers by the lawes of
<pb facs="tcp:135564:17"/> equyte &amp; iuſtyce be compelled to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne and to punyſhe with deathe. Wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly tranquyllyte reſte and peace of all this your realme ſoueraygne lorde / and the good order of the ſame hangeth and reſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th moche vpon the godly and dyligent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutyon of the office of paſtors and of the ſpirituall ſhepherds dewly called and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted accordinge to Godes worde. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behoueth the preſenter of the clercke to a benefyce and cure of ſowles to be cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect and well ware what clerke he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th preſent / and that he haue good knowle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>age experience and proue of his clercke be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he preſent hym. For if a paſtour doo not feade the flocke of Chriſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to his charge / the deathe of their ſowles ſhalbe required of his handes. As the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete Ezechiell ſayeth in the .xxxiij.<note place="margin">Ezech. xxxiij.</note> chapi. And if the patron willingely / other for kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred / fauoure / frendſhippe / ſeruice or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney / preſent a clerke which he knoweth not to be ſo lerned in Gods worde / that he be able to inſtructe and teache the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to his charge bothe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lawe of God and withe the goſpell / every ſuche patron co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteth to the deathe &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſowles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to the charge of ſuche vnlerned preſte. And therfore ſuche a
<pb facs="tcp:135564:18"/> Patron ſhall alſo be punyſhed with lyke payne / whiche is eternall / as the Apoſtell ſayeth.<note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> Not onely they that doo euill / but alſo they whiche conſent therunto ſhalbe punyſhed with lyke payne. What wyſe man liuynge wolde hyer a ſhepherde to gouerne hys beaſtly &amp; worldly ſhepe which nother wolde nor coulde feade / handle / ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue nor ones ſee his ſhepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to his charge. Suche a wyſe ſhepherde wolde ſhortely make his maſters profet come to lytle aduauntage. Surely a wyſe man wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de choſe no ſuche ſhepherde. And if he were deceyued through the perſuaſyon of ſome of his frendes / yet when he hathe proued that he hathe no connynge nor dyli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gence / he will ſhortely dyſcharge hym of his cure and ſeruice. Shall we be eſtemed chriſten men whiche haue more te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der loue and affectyon to owre corruptyble profett / than we haue to the honowre of God &amp; the eternall wealthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> immortall ſowles of owre chriſten bretheren / whom Gode commaundeth to loue as owre ſelfe.<note place="margin">Io. xxi.</note> Chriſt ded not commytt to Peter the cure and charge of his ſhepe before he aſked thryſe of Peter whether he loued hym. As who ſhulde ſaye. I wolde not commytt my beſt beloued Ioywell and treaſure vnto the / 
<pb facs="tcp:135564:18"/> vnleſſe thowe loue me hartely. I wolde wyſhe that all gouernowres and rulers in this caſe wolde take example and folowe Chriſt whiche knowynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Good wyll of Peters harte / yet as one ingnora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te therof ded demaunde this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Peter before he ded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure of his flocke to hym / therby to geue example &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon doctryne to all his faythfull folowers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde haue ſuche tender and feruent loue towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des the Chriſten ſowles / that they wolde not commytt the gouernaunce and cure of them to any man / but vnto ſuche of whom they haue proue &amp; ſure knowleage / that aſwell by their preachinge &amp; ſyncere tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of Gods worde / as alſo by their ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſe lyuinge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonante to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame worde they had vnfaynedly a faythfull harty loue towardes Chryſtes flocke. A blynde eye which can not dyrecte and leade the bodye is a blemyſhe and a burden to the naturall bodye / and noo commodyte. In lykewyſe a man choſen to be a ſpyrytuall Paſtour which hathe not the knowleage and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to preache the lawe and the goſpell / is but a blynde eye not able to dyrecte and leade the ſpyrytuall bodye. Wherfore if any patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> choſe any ſuche ingnora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a paſtoure / a ſpirituall eye and light
<pb facs="tcp:135564:19"/> to leade the ſpirituall ſowles / he not onely deceyueth them but alſo aſmoche as lyeth in hym kyllethe the bodye / and dothe grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te iniurye to Chriſtes bloode. Now it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye pleaſe yowre highnes to note and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke what myſchef and inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyence folowe the electyon and admyſſion of an ingno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante poſtour. Fyrſte if an ingnorante by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope in Gods worde be admytted / he can not execute his office becauſe he knoweth not the ſcryptures whiche teacheth hym what ſhulde perteyne to his owne office. And as the byſhop is ignorante in Godes worde / ſo he admytteth ſuche as be vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Gods worde / evyn ſuche as by noo poſſybylite can execute the office of their callinge. Idle parſons / vnhappy / droncker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / ſwerers / common players at all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thryftye games / in whom there is no cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyre / noo humylyte / iuſtyce / nor temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. For a concluſion / ſuche they admytte in whom there is noo holynes / godly doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / nor good example of lyuinge. To ſuche they commytte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> healthe of ſowles / the flocke of Chriſte dearely bought with his bloode / by ſuche ydle and wicked harlottes the enheritaunce of Chriſte is troden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fote. All euyll condycions maners and doctrynes by them be tawght / ſo that in
<pb facs="tcp:135564:19"/> the ſteade of holy ſcripture is crepte in the doctryne of lyes / all ſuperſtycions / dead &amp; vayne ceremonyes / and lycence to doo all kynde of ſynne. Some of the blynde igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante preſtes teache the people that God is honowred / and ſoules releued of their paynes through the rynginge of belles / painting of poſtes / and ſettynge vp tapers and candelles before the ſayd poſtes / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the blynde preſtes doo bothe ſence &amp; ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle with holy water. An other ſorte of blyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſhauelings teache the people to gett he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with taſtynge / this preſcripte daye &amp; that daye / with trentalles and maſſes of ſcala celi / with forbearinge of bodely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes &amp; kepinge ydle holy dayes / they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che muche holynes and Gods ſeruice to ſtande in their holy oyle / holy creame / holy water / holy aſſhes / hallowed bedes / mumb<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge of a numbre of pſalmes in laten / kea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinge of church ales in the whiche with leappynge / daunſynge / and kyſſyng they maynteyne the profett of their churche (to the honoure of God as they both ſaye and thyncke.) And thus the blynde leadeth the blynde / that both fall hedlonge into the la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of eternall brenninge fyer. What natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall harte is there whiche will not lamente the miſery / yea the dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly
<pb facs="tcp:135564:20"/> thretenede by Gods worde vnto all ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norante and neglygent byſſhopps and other ſpyrytuall ſhepherdes which doo not dylygently execute theyr offyce and vocation? What honeſt louinge harte doth not bewayle the habundaunce of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / the longe myſerable blyndnes wherin this realme hath ben ledd and wrapped in through the yngnorancye and neglygence of ſuche blynde guydes. But is there any chryſten harte which can forbere contynuall ſyghinge and mornynge / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membringe the multytude yea the infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte numbre of ſowles (whiche without the greate mercye of God paſſinge all his worckes) through ingnorancye &amp; neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of ſuche blynde ſhepherdes / be vtterly caſt awaye &amp; dampned. What good cyuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le harte wolde not I ſaye lament and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle the greate burden wherwith this your realme (gracyouſe lorde) is ouerchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged through the greate multytude of chauntery preſtes / ſoule preſtes / chanons / reſydenſaryes in chathedrall churches / prebendaryes / muncke pencyons / moro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we mas preſtes / vnlerned curattes / pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of gyldes and of fraternytees or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhedes / rydinge Chaplaynes / and ſuche other ydle parſons / whyche yf
<pb facs="tcp:135564:20"/> they be well noted / and alſo what frute ſpryngethe of them indyffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly valewed / conſydered / and pondered / it will appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re manyfeſtly to all reaſonable and godly wyttes / that they do brynge noo maner commodyte profett or vtylyte other ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall or temporall to this your publycke wealthe. No / no / they be not onely no commodyte nor profett to the common wealthe / but rather moche hynderance. And truly no lytle waſters / ſpoylers / and robbers / and that of the moſt poore / in dyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and neadye of youre louinge ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / which be moſt craftely / ſubtelly / and vnrightuouſely depryued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charytable ſuccoure and almes of many ſymple vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerned innocentes / through a vayne hope and falſe confydence that theyr ſowles ſhulde be releued and releaſed of theyr paynes and tormentes dewe for theyr ſynnes / when they be departed this worlde / by the longe prayers of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. And (the more it is to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) noo lytle nombre of your ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes through ſuche vngodly truſte and confydence in maſſes and dyryges to be ſonge and celebrated for them when they be dead / be greatly encoraged to lyue both wickedly towardes God / and
<pb facs="tcp:135564:21"/> alſo vnfrutefully towardes the worlde / lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le remembrynge and eſtemynge their voca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion &amp; callinge wherin God hath appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to walke / and moche leſſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame neceſſyte of their chriſten brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. This vayne hope in the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge prayers of preſtes (no doubt graciouſe lorde) is a greate occaſyon of moche pouerte amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the poore and neady of this yowr realme. For the ſpedy remedy of this pouerte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt your louinge ſubiectes / and the vtter ſuppreſſyon of ſuche vayne hope in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers of preſtes to be made for your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes when they be deade / whiche is the greate cauſe of this myſerable pouerte / it may pleaſe your mageſtye of your accuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med goodnes to call to your graciouſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that all the people of this your regyon be ſubiect vnto yowr gracyouſe power / rule / and dominion as vnto their ſupreme hedd and gouernowre dewly by God appointed to gouerne them onely du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge their naturall lyues / but when it pleaſeth God to take their ſowles owt of this myſerable worlde / than yowr grace is dyſcharged of all gouernance / cure &amp; char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as of ſuche which after their death doo not appertayne to yowr grace / nor be of your Kyngedome / but onely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:135564:21"/> Kyngedome of God, vnder his gouernaunce prouyſion and rule. Into the whyche Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedome nother your grace nor noo other erthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prynce maye lawfullye vſurpe or take anye rule prouiſyon care or gouernance, for the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les entered therunto. Seynge that your grace haue no auctoryte nor power ouer the ſoules departed, you be not onelye dyſcharged to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne to care or to prouyde for them beinge deade, but muche rather to prouyde that they maye not be deceyuedde ſo vnder the coloure of longe prayer, but that they maye be taughte ſyncerelye GODS worde whyle they be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge vnder youre ſubiection ſo that they maye beleue conſtantelye and lyue godlye, and then by Chriſtes promeſſe bell gates ſhall not preuayle agaynſte them, moche leſſe they ſhal haue any neade of ſuche ſtraunge ſuccoure and helpe of menne, nothynge appoyntedde nor taughte by Goddes worde to be profitable or neceſſarye fortheyre ſoules after theyre deathe. Wherfore I myſtruſte not butte that youre mageſtye when you ſhall nexte intreate for the reformation of the enormytyes and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſpronge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vp in the chriſtenne religion, you wyll godlye reforme ſuche abuſe and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> couetouſenes, and certeynelye beynge to godlye remedye nor helpe for ſowles depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:135564:22"/> whiche hathe noo ſtrengthe nor effycacye of GODS worde, whyche is the verye trewe foundacion of all the Chriſten religion and helpe for ſoules. And in the meane ſeaſon I doo no leſſe thyncke and alſo praye hartelye to GOD that youre mageſtye wyll prouyde and make ordinaunce, that all ſuche landes and poſſeſſyons whervpon ſo manye ydle hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pochrytes and deceyuers be greate burdeyne and charge to youre realme, whyche hytherto haue lyued vngodly and vnprofytablely, maye from henceforthe be partelye conuerted to the ſupportation and mayntenaunce of common ſtooles, whereby erroures crepte vp throughe ingnorance maye be throughe knoweledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſedde, and godlye learnynge and knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge more plenteouſlye planted and admyniſtred and partelye that youre poore louynge ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes maye be more mercyfullye releued and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, whyle they lyue vnder youre ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on charge and gouernaunce. Thys godlye dyſtrybution (moſt prudent Soueraygne) of the landes and poſſeſſions ordeynedde and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntedde for the comforte ſuccours and helpe of yowre poore louynge and lyuynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, is muche more conſonante and agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to GODDES worde and more certayne dyſcharge of youre graces conſcyence then to
<pb facs="tcp:135564:22"/> ſuffer the ſame poſſeſſions to be vngodly caſte awaye and conſumed vnder ſuche falſe colow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and pretence to releue ſowles departed, of whome youre mageſtye haue nother cure nor charge, nor can not aſſure to them by God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde throughe ſuche longe prayers of preſtes releſſe of paynes after their deathe, or anye other ayde comforte or ſuccoure. For wythoute anye doubte (gracyouſe Lorde) yf ſuche hyredde prayers hadde bene godlye and neceſſarye for the ſowles departedde, other Chryſte or his Apoſtelles wolde haue taughts it, or at the leaſt haue prayſed or practiſedde it, and not ſo manifeſtlye reproued and thretened it, ſayenge.<note place="margin">Marc. xii.</note> Beware of them whych deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re wyddowes howſes vnder coloure of longe prayerres, theyre iudgemente ſhalbe muche longer. In all the newe Teſtamente the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is no mencyonne made of anye ſuche offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer nor offyce inſtitutedde nor appoyntedde to praye for the deade. And yet all menne I thyncke wyll confeſſe that the truethe of GODS worde was mooſte ſyncerelye ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forthe and preached in the tyme of Chryſte and of his Apoſtelles, in whoſe tyme there was no ſuche craftye learnynge publyſhedde nor taughte by them, nor longe tyme after.</p>
            <p>But then menne ſtablyſhedde and grounded
<pb facs="tcp:135564:23"/> their religion and hope of healthe vpon God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, whyche teachethe vs that who ſo beleuethe is ſaued and hathe no neade of longe preſtyſhe prayers, and who ſo beleuethe not, ſhalbe condempned. Betwene theſe extreame contraries there is no meane, as ſaint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſayethe.<note place="margin">Note here. s. Auguſt in hys boke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyteled Hypog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſtico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fol. ix.</note> Wherfore I exhorte all them (whiche contrary to all holy ſcriptures) truſte to the thyrd place &amp; there to haue releaſe of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes throughe the ſonge prayers of preaſtes, that they wolde geue ouer ſuche fayned fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye of men (ſubtilly ymagyned onely throughe inſaciable couetouſenes of ambiciouſe preſtes to gette moneye (therewythe to mayneteyne theyr vngodlye luſtes, and to lyue ydlely and delycately and to truſte rather to the ſure and infallyble trewethe of Goddes worde, whyche wythoute doubte is to repent and beleue, and vtterlye to forſake all ſynne, and than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantelye to truſte to Goddes promeſſe of mercye. Here manifeſtly apperethe ſouerayg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Lorde, in what myſerable blyndenes the mooſte parte of this youre realme haue longe tyme be led, yea and almoſt drowned throughe the longe cuſtome vſed therin. Who is it that can not lamente (I ſaye) this deplorate and miſerable ſorte of blynde ſhepherdes? Be not they boughte withe the ſame price wherwythe
<pb facs="tcp:135564:23"/> wede bought to be members of one bodye wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of Chriſt is heade. If we be members of one bodye certeynlye we can not then but caſte and feale not onely theyr euyll, but alſo the lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table eſtate of all other caſt awaye through the Lorde I truſte the punyſhment is pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withe thou hall threatned the worlde to be pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhedde wythe hunger and chryſte not wythe hunger and thryſte of breade and drynke,<note place="margin">Amos. viii.</note> but for lacke of hearynge thy worde. Yt is nowe tyme lorde to ſhewe thyne accuſtomedde good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and mercye, for the whyche we doo dayly and hartelye praye, ſayenge. Throughe the tender mercye of God wherwithe he hathe dyſyred vs,<note place="margin">Luce. i</note> geue lyghte to vs whych fyfte in darckenes and in the ſhaddowe of deathe, to guyde oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into the waye of peace.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is a daungerouſe thynge to admitte one to be aſpyrytuall paſtoure whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon and ſtudye all hys youthe hathe bene in decrees and popyſhe lawes. For ſuche a ſtudye for the mooſte parte ingenderethe a popyſhe harte. If any ſuche be admittedde to be a paſtoure, he ſhall not onelye other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely in confeſſyon or by ſome other craftye meanes, poyſon hys flocke with mans tradi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions and popyſhe doctrine, but all ſhall aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente the popiſhe power, forthe abrogacion
<pb facs="tcp:135564:24"/> wherof youre grace and youre honorable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell haue taken greate paynes and trauayle.</p>
            <p>Nowe eftſones I truſte that all men whyche reade this lytle boke ſhal perceyue therby what inconuenyence and dampnable euyll enſeweth the vngodlye preſentacyon and admyſſyon of the vnlearned in Goddes worde, and carnall preſtes to ſpirituall offyces. And althoughe ſuche Patrons haue lytle zeale and loue to the common and publyke wealthe, yet for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler and carnall loue whyche they beare to theyr clerkes (whome they addycte and bynde ſurelye to eternall dampnacion, yf they geue them ſuche ſpyrytuall offyces, whyche they neyther canne nor wyll excute and perfourme or for the tender zeale and loue whyche they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue to the ſoules ſo derely boughte withe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bloode, they wyll wyth all circumſpection prou etheyr clerkes that they be not onelye well learned in Goddes worde but that they alſo haue taken greate paynes in preachynge the fame, and that they haue alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to theyr preachynge. Suche expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and proue was commaunded to be made of weddowes, before they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to lyue vpon the charge of the congregacyon. As it appearethe in Tymotheye.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Ti. v.</note>Muche more than euydente and ſure proue
<pb facs="tcp:135564:24"/> of Paſtoures (whoſe offyce is ſoo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) ſhoulde be hadde and made before they be admyttedde to theyr ſpyrytuall offyce and charge. And althoughe the election of the Byſſhoppe and of other ſpyrytuall Paſtours in euery paynte be hadde and done accordynge as I haue before wrytten, yet (mooſt dreade ſoueraygne Lorde) I ſee twoo fowle deformy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and greate lamentable myſchefes annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the vocacyon and offyce of Byſſhoppes, whyche not refourmedde wyll poyſon and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye corrupte the godlye vocacyon and elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of the ſayde Byſſhops. The one infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and peſtylente poyſonne is there greate Lordeſhyppes and domynions wythe the yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely prouentes of the ſame. Whyche hath ſo faſſhynonedde them in proude countenaunces and worldelye behauoure, that nowe they be moſte lyke to the Heathen Prynces and moſte vnlyke vnto Chriſte, althoughe they woulde be eſteamedde of al men to be hys trewe ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoures, yet poore Chryſte ſayethe. The foxes haue hooles, the byrdes of the ayre haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, but the ſonne of manne hathe not wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in to laye hys heade. But oure Byſſhops haue gorgeouſe and ſumptuouſe buylded how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes maners and caſtelles pleaſauntelye ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> parches well repleniſhed wyth deare,
<pb facs="tcp:135564:25"/> warrens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> full of conyes, and fyſſhe pooles well ſcored wyth dyuerſe kyndes of fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. And not onelye theſe commoddities and pleaſures, but alſo diuerſe other pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Howe this Lordely and worldely Byſſhop lyke eſtate agreeth wyth Chriſtes wordes, I thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a man can not reaſonablye conyecture or ymagen by theyr countenaunce and lyuynge, that they be Chriſtes trewe diſciples. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther myſchefe and euell is that they haue to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny worldly c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res and buſynes. For to theſe manners and Lordeſhyppes belonge manye tenauntes, for whoſe leaſes to be made fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and haryottes to be appoyntedde and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, a mercyamentes to be affeſſed taxed and alſo forgeuen and diſpencedde, there be noo fewe ſutes made to my Lorde Byſſhoppe, alſo the hearynge of teſtamentorye cauſes, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorſes, cauſes of matrymonye, of ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, adulterye, and punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſuche other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> courte matters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whereof not one belonge to hys offyce and vocacion appoynted by Goddes worde. My lorde byſhoppe is ſo occupyed and vnquycted, that he hathe noo leaſure to ſtudye nor to preache GODS worde. But ſuche affayres and worldelye buſynes nothynge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneynge to hys vocation be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> greate
<pb facs="tcp:135564:25"/> hynderance and lett to my lorde Byſhop that he can not applye hym to exercyſe his owne offyce.<note place="margin">Mat. v</note> For no man can ſerue two maſters ſayeth Chriſt. The Apoſtles thought it not iuſte and equall to prouide for the neceſſary lyuinge of the poore / lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge Godds worde vntawght.<note place="margin">Act. vi.</note> But my lorde Byſhoppe doinge theſe things no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing perteyninge to his office / thincketh that he hathe exactely done his offyce. From theſe greate maners commeth ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely greate rentes pleaſures &amp; profettes / which althowghe they be the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God / yet thabundaunce of them (beinge where they be more impedyment than helpe) be a greate occaſyon of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in the vſer of them. And peraduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they wolde allure and intyſe a Byſhops harte to truſte in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſo corrupte hym / as the ſcripture ſayeth. Bleſſed is the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che which is founde withowt blemyſhe &amp; hathe not gone after golde nor hoped in money and treaſures / where is there ſuche a one and we ſhall commende hym and call hym bleſſed / for greate things dothe he amonge his people. And if my lorde Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe ſhulde geue the ſuperfluyte of his goodes to the poore (whoſe goodes iuſtely they be) as the Prophete Ezay ſayethe / <note place="margin">☜ Eſa. iij.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:135564:26"/> Than my lorde ſhulde lacke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to furny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe his lordely countenaunce / and ſo my lorde ſhulde looſe his lordely honoure and prayſe of the worlde Wherfore as theſe ſuperfluouſe poſſeſſions be annexed to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Byſſhops by mans vayne fantaſye and not by Gods worde / ſo my lorde Byſhoppe wyll other keape them to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke hym more fryndes / remembrynge that ryches makethe many fryndes / but the poore is forſaken of his neyghbowre / or deuyſe the exſpence of them contrary to Godes worde / other to make ſure fryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in the courte aboute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge to obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne more promocions &amp; benefices / or in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſe buyldinge / ſumptuouſe and delyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te fare / well appareled ſeruauntes / try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me decked horſes to ryde pompeouſely ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a lorde. Althoughe there were no auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torite to proue this / yet the lordely counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce &amp; faſſhyon of byſhops / yea their common exercyſe and alſo practyſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well proue and teſtyfye this playnely before the face of all men which knoweth the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delynes of byſſhopps. As the Prophete Ezay ſayethe.<note place="margin">Eſa. iij.</note> The chaungynge of their countenaunce bewrayeth them / yea they declare theyr owne ſynnes them ſelfes as ſodomytes / and hyed them not. Doo
<pb facs="tcp:135564:26"/> not theſe thinges fayntely agree with the ſayenge of theyr predeceſſour Paule the Apoſtle which ſayeth.<note place="margin">i. Ti. vi.</note> When we haue foode and raymente we muſte be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented. Is not this lordely honoure dyrectely agaynſte Chryſtes wordes / which ſayethe.<note place="margin">Iu. xxij.</note> The Kynges of nacyons raygne ouer them / and they that haue auctoryte ouer them are called graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe lordes. But yow ſhall not be ſo. Alſo Peter ſpeakethe to his trewe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoures ſayenge. Feade yow Chriſtes flocke aſmuche as lyeth in yow / takynge the ouerſyght of them not as compelled therunto / but wyllyngelye / after a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorte / nor for the deſyer of fylthy luker / but of a good mynde / not as thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe yowe were lordes ouer the paryſhes / but that yowe be an example to the flocke / and that withe good will. But owre lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely Byſhops eſtate and proude coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of lyuynge (as it is nowe vſed) is contrarye to Godes worde / as it appearethe by theſe wordes. But yow ſhall not be ſo. And alſo by theſe ſayengs. Not as thoughe yow were lordes ouer the paryſhes.<note place="margin">Math. xij.</note> And Chryſt ſayethe. He that is not with me / is a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſte me. Wherefore ſo longe
<pb facs="tcp:135564:27"/> as they raigne ſo lordely in the clergie con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to Godds worde / ſo longe be they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte God. And ſo longe as they be aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſte God / they be not ſente from God / and then can they not preache trewly and ſyncerely his morde. For howe can they preache excepte they be ſente ſayeth Paul.<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> Chriſte was ſente to preache as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe. Marc. i. Luce. iiij. and Ezaye. lxi. And Chriſte ſayeth to all his trewe dyſciples. As my father ſente me / ſo I do ſende yow.<note place="margin">Ioan. ij</note> And commaundeth alſo all his Apoſtles &amp; trewe ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles to preache the goſpell to the holle worlde and not lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely to raigne in the clergye. Whom Paul teacheth to be as myniſters / ſayeng. Lett a man this wiſe eſteame vs / euyn as the my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſte and the ſtuardes of the ſecretes of God.<note place="margin">i. Cor. .iiij.</note> To preache the goſpell therfore (moſt gracyouſe and prudente lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de) is the trewe vocacyon and offyce of all godly Byſhops / Parſons / Vycars and of other ſhepherdes / and not to be enbaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowrs to prynces / nor to be iudges to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re matters of contencyon / teſtamentarye cauſes / dyuorſes / ſelaunders / bawdery / and ſuche other. Your grace hathe of your laye fee ſuffycient bothe in lerninge and wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and of good conſcyence to here and
<pb facs="tcp:135564:27"/> iudge ſuche cauſes and varyaunces / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myttynge Byſhops to attende their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce and vocacyon by God (and not by man) appoynted. And therfore they ſhulde not excercyſe any other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce than God hathe appoynted to them.<note place="margin">Mat. vi</note> For no man can ſerue two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. And if Byſhops and other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoures wolde dyligently execute theyr vocacyon and offyce / moche fewer of theſe matters of contencyon ſhalbe in vre and experience other to be harde or iudged. Seinge the ſcriptures commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth ſo erneſtly euery man to walke as he is called. Many Chriſten men mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell gretly why the Byſhops deſyre and procure ſo greadely to exercyſe the offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce perteyninge to an other vocacyon / and to leue their vocacyon and offyce (appoynted by God to them to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſed) not executed nor performed and done.<note place="margin">Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ix.</note> Verely bycauſe they loue the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of men / more then the glorye of God. And ſurely euen as Cayphas and Annas beinge Byſhops and exercyſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the offyce of ſeculer and temporall iudges ded iudge Chriſt to be crucifyed / ſo owr Byſhops ſo longe as they contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye
<pb facs="tcp:135564:28"/> to their callynge doo exercyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of temporall iudges / ſo longe ſhall they perſecute Chriſte and his membres / and ſtudye to ſuppreſſe his worde / and not to preache the ſame. Haue not they buſynes ſuffycyent wherwith to occupye them in their owne offyce? If they wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de loke well therunto / doo not they ſee on euery ſyde deteſtable ſynne raigne throughowt all this your realme. Is there not ſuche exceſſe and coſtelynes of apparell / bycauſe of dyuerſyte and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of faſſhyons that ſcarce a worſhipfull mans landes which in tymes paſte was wonte to fynde and maynteyne twenty or thirty tall powemen / a good plenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full howſholde for the releyfe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force of many poore and neadye / and the ſame nowe is not ſuffycyent and able to maynteyne the heyre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame landes / his wiffe / her gentle woman or mayde / two yowmen / and one lackey. The pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypall cauſe herof is their coſtly apparell / and ſpecially their manyfolde and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe chaunges of faſſhyons whiche the man and ſpecially the woman muſte wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vpon bothe headde and bodye. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme cappe / ſomtyme hoode / nowe the
<pb facs="tcp:135564:28"/> frenſhe faſſhyon / nowe the ſpanyſhe faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyon / than the Italyan faſſhyon / and then the myllen faſſhyon / ſo that there is noo ende of conſumynge of ſubſtaunce and that vaynely and all to pleaſe the prowde folyſhe man and womens fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye. Hereof ſpryngethe great myſerye and neade. The fathers conſumynge theyr goodes in vayne / pryde / and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton luſtes (called vpon by yowr grace to ſerue yowr mageſtye for the defence of this yowr realme) haue not to doo their dewtye / wherby they be compelled to ſell theyr landes / or els to burdeyne their fryndes / or els to daunger them ſelfe in dette to many. Hereof ryſethe it that the father is compelled to declare his will vpon hys landes to be executed after his deathe (when he can not occupye the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me hym ſelfe) for the aduauncement and helpe of his children and the payment of his dettes / whom eaſely he myght in his lyffe haue aduaunced holpen and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged / yf ſuche ryotuouſe expenſes had ben auoyded.<note place="margin">Oſe. iiij</note> The Prophete Oſee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yethe. There is noo trewethe / no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye / no knowleage of God in earthe / curſynge / lyenge / murdre-thefte / adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terye
<pb facs="tcp:135564:29"/> hathe broken in / and yet doo owre ſhepherdes holde theyr peace. What commeſſacyon / dronckenes / deteſtable ſwearinge by all the partes of Chriſtes bodye (and yet callynge them in ſcorne huntinge othes) extorcyon / pryde / couetuouſenes / and ſuche other deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vyce raigne in this yowr realme / agaynſte the whiche owre Byſhops and other Paſtoures ſhulde contynually crye owt / as the Prophete ſayethe.<note place="margin">Eſa. v.</note> Crye nowe as lowed as thow canſte / leaue not of / lyfte vp thy voyce lyke a trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pett / and ſhewe my people their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and the howſe of Iacob their ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But alas they be become bothe blynde and dome / as the Prophete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yethe.<note place="margin">Eſaye. lxvi.</note> His watchmen are all blynde they haue all together noo vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge / they are all dome dogges not able to barcke / they are ſlepye / folyſhe are they and lye ſnortinge / they are ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meles dogges that be neuer ſatyſfyed. The ſhepherdes alſo in lyke maner haue no vnderſtandinge / but euery man tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethe his owne waye / euery one after his owne couetuouſenes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. What is the cauſe that they doo
<pb facs="tcp:135564:29"/> not execute this their offyce? Other by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can not / or bycauſe they haue ſomoche worldely buſynes that they will not apply them ſelfes to perfourme bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. Or els they be afrayed to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the trwethe / leſt they ſhulde dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe men. Whom Paul reproueth ſayenge. If I ſhulde pleaſe men I ſhulde not be the ſeruaunte of Chriſte.<note place="margin">Gal. i. Pſal. lij</note> Alſo the Prophete ſayethe. God breakethe the bones of them whiche ſtudye to pleaſe men / they be confounded / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the lorde diſpyſeth them. Not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withſtandynge owr byſhops loue ſo well their greate domynions wherby they maynteyne their lordely honoure / that they will not dyſpleaſe men with prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge the treuth / leſt they ſhulde then looſe their greate poſſeſſyons / and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequently their lordely glorye. But ſurely as longe as they poſſeſſe theyr greate domynions / ſo longe they wyll contynewe and maynteyne their pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. And ſo longe as they contynewe in pryde / ſo longe they ſhall not receyue the holy ghoſte / whiche ſhall teach-them to ſpeake the treuthe. For vpon whom ſhall my ſprete reaſte (ſayeth the
<pb facs="tcp:135564:30"/> Prophete Eſaye) but vpon the meake and lowely / and vpon hym which fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe my ſayengs.<note place="margin">Eſa. vi.</note> Alſo the Prophete ſayeth. God reſyſteth the prowde / and vnto the meake and lowely he geuethe his grace. Wherfore ſo longe as the byſhops contynewe in this worldely we althe and honowre / ſo longe will they neuer do their dewtye and offyce / but rather perſecute the worde of God whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che declarethe and ſhewethe what is their offyce and their dewtye. And ſo longe as they do not exercyſe their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce and vocatyon / but doo perſecute the worde and ſuche as ſyncerely preache the ſame / ſo longe ſhall ſynne increaſe. For if the eye be wicked / all the body ſhalbe full of darcknes. For euen as at ſuche tyme when the Byſhoppe of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me was fyrſte endowed with greate poſſeſſyons / a voyce was harde / ſeyinge. Nowe venome and poyſon is caſte and ſhed forthe into the churche of God. In lykewyſe no doubt moſt godly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernoure / ſemblable voyce and ſayenge maye be veryfyed in and vpon all the churche of Englande / ſythen yowr By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were endowed with ſo greate poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyons
<pb facs="tcp:135564:30"/> and lordely domynions. No dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bt gracyous lorde / ſo longe as grete lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely domynions / wordely honours and wealthe / be anexed and knyt to the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon and offyces of Byſhops and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſtours / theſe myſcheues &amp; incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces ſhall euer enſue &amp; folowe. Fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte the moſte prowde and ambycyouſe / the moſte couetuouſe and wycked / which other by money frendſhyp or flattery can obtayne the benefyce / wyll laboure with all ſtudy and polycye to gett the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice / only for the worldely honoure and not for the zeale and loue which he ſhulde haue to enſtructe and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the people commytted to his cure and charge. And for the profett which belongethe and apperteynethe to the ſame benefyce / they wyll dyſſemble hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylyte and deſpeccyon of all worldely profettes and pleaſures / ſo colorablye and ſubtelly / that yt ſhall be very har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for youre mageſtye or any other hauynge aucthoryte to geue benefyces to perceyue them. And when they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue obteyned the benefyce / than euery Chriſten man ſhall well perceyue that he hathe not entered in by the dore: that
<pb facs="tcp:135564:31"/> is for the zeale and loue to doo and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the offyce / but hathe clymmed vp and aſſended by a nother waye / that ys for the luker and honoure annexed to the offyce. And than certenly whoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer aſſendeth and enterethe in by a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waye / can not be but a thefe / by daye and by nyght / whoſe ſtudy and laboure muſte be to ſteale / kyll / and to deſtroy. As Chriſte (whoſe wordes muſte euer be true) ſayethe. The the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe commethe not but to ſteale / to kyll / and to deſtroye.<note place="margin">Ioan. x.</note> So that ſo longe as ſo moche worldely profett and honoure be longethe to the benefyce: ſo longe wyll he that for wante and lacke of lernynge can not doo the offyce / and alſo the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte couetuouſe and proude / wyll labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to haue the offyce / whereby the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple commytted to his cure / ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be vntawgth / and not lerned in Gods worde / but alſo all they which can prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che and teache Godds worde and loue the ſame / by ſuche a worldely wolfe / ſhall be extremely perſecuted and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For he can not but ſteale / kyll / and deſtroye / and vtterly abhore / and hate the godly / as Chriſte ſayethe. Yf you
<pb facs="tcp:135564:31"/> were of the worlde / the worlde wolde loue his owne. But becauſe you be not of the worlde / but I haue choſen you from the worlde / therfore the worlde dothe hate you. No doubt a man ſhall moche rather vpon thornes gather grapes / and vpon brambles and bryres gather fygges / than of ſoche gredy the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to haue any Chryſten relygyon: other ſetforthe / preached / or ſtablyſhed. Wherfore (moſte redoubted Prynce) ſein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that theyr greate poſſeſſyons / ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches / worldely offyces / cures / and buſynes / be the impedyment and let that they do not execute theyr vocacyon and offyce / whiche is ſo godly profytable and neceſſarye for this yowr common wealthe / yowe beinge owr ſoueraigne lorde and Kynge (whom God hathe cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led to gouerne this yowr realme / and to redreſſe the enormytyes and abuſes of the ſame) by all iuſtyce and equyte are bounden to take awaye from Byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes and other ſpirytuall ſhepherdes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſuperfluyte of poſſeſſyons and ryches and other ſeculer cures buſynes and worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely offyces / whiche be the cauſe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſynne in them / and no leſſe occaſyon
<pb facs="tcp:135564:32"/> whereby they be letted to execute their offyce / to the greate loſſe and hynderan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of moche faythe vertue and goodnes / which myght be admyniſtred to your ſubiectes / through the trew preachynge of Godes worde. And that done / than circumſpectly to take heade that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne be admytted to be Paſtoures / but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preache and haue preached ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerely Godes worde. And all ſuche as will not / to remoue them from theyr cures. This godly ordre obſerued in the electy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpirituall paſtoures / and the peſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent poyſon moued and taken away from theyr vocatyon / faithe ſhall increaſe / and ſynne ſhall decreaſe / trewe obedience ſhall be obſerued wyth all humylite to your mageſtye and to the hygher powers by your grace appoynted in office. Cyuile quyetnes reſte and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſhalbe ſtablyſhed / God ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be feared honoured and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / whiche is theffec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten lyuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lorde ſaue our moſte ſoueraygne lorde Kynge Henry the eyght / and graunte that he may ones throughly fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le and perceyue what myſerable calamy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſorowe &amp; wretchednes we ſuffer now in theſe dayes a brode in the countre / by theſe vnlerned / popyſhe / and moſte cruell tyrauntes / euen the very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of Chryſtes croſſe / whoſe payne ſhall be withowt ende / whan we ſhall lyue in Ioye for euer. Graunte yet ones agayne I ſay goode lorde and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte mercyfull father through thy ſone Iheſus Chriſte / that whan his grace ſhall knowe and perceyue (by thy gyfte &amp; goodnes) theyr moſt deteſtable wayes in myſuſynge thy heretage / that he wyll erneſtly go aboute to ſe a redreſſe amonge them / and to the penytent and contryte in harte to ſhewe his accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med goodnes / and to the other his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce / accordinge to ſaynt Paules doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / and his graces lawes.</p>
            <p>And moſte dreade ſoueraygne (with all humylyte and humblenes of harte) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche your grace / (accordinge to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed goodnes) to take this my rude
<pb facs="tcp:135564:33"/> ſupplycacyon to the beſte / as a frute of my obedyence / wheryn I haue not dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled / but haue opened fully vnto your grace the grounde and very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my hart / not of any grudge euyll wyll or malyce that I beare to any ſpirytuall ſhepherde (God I take to recorde) but onely for the glory of God / the honoure of your gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / and the wealthe and profett of your moſte naturall and louinge ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Enprynted in the yeare of our Lorde. M.CCCCC.xliiij. in the moneth of Decembre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135564:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
